<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lamentations for the death of the late illustrious Prince Henry: and the dissolution of his religious familie Two sermons: preached in his Highnesse chappell at Saint Iames, on the 10. and 15. day of Nouember, being the first Tuesday and Sunday after his decease. By Daniel Price, chaplaine then in attendance.</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115213</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850432</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850432</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1331:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lamentations for the death of the late illustrious Prince Henry: and the dissolution of his religious familie Two sermons: preached in his Highnesse chappell at Saint Iames, on the 10. and 15. day of Nouember, being the first Tuesday and Sunday after his decease. By Daniel Price, chaplaine then in attendance.</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Snodham, for Roger Iackson, and are to be sould at his shop neere to Fleetstreet Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Lamentations vpon the death of the late Prince Henry.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry Frederick, --  Prince of Wales, 1594-1612.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:1"/>
            <p>LAMENTATIONS <hi>FOR</hi> the death of the late Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince <hi>Henry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> the diſſolution of his religious Familie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two Sermons:</hi> Preached in his Highneſſe Chappell at Saint IAMES, on the 10. and 15. day of <hi>Nouember,</hi> being the firſt Tueſday and Sunday after his deceaſe.</p>
            <p>By DANIEL PRICE, Chaplaine then in attendance.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MICAH 7.8.</bibl> 
               <hi>Reioyce not againſt me, O mine enemie, though I fall I ſhall riſe againe.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by THO. SNODHAM, for ROGER IACKSON, and are to be ſould at his ſhop neere to Fleetſtreet Conduit. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:2"/>
            <p>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY PRINCE, PRINCE <hi>CHARLES,</hi> THE IOY OF OVR SORROW AND THE HOPE OF SVCCESSION, ENGLANDS <hi>CHARLEMAINE,</hi> DANIEL PRICE, WITH THE DEDICATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON OF THESE, HIS TWO MITES, WISHETH, THE ACCRVMENT OF ALL HAPPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESSE, WITH THE DOVBLING OF THE SPIRIT, OF HIS BLESSED BROTHER VPON HIM.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Religious, and worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, the great <hi>Officers</hi> to the late renowmed Prince.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Ho. worthy, Gentlemen of the <hi>Bed-chamber:</hi> to his Reuerend Brethren the Chaplaines; and to all the reſt of the Gentlemen and Officers of that <hi>Princely familie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He importunity</hi> of ſome, the <hi>expectation</hi> of many, and the kinde <hi>acceptation</hi> of all of you, hath cauſed me to caſt theſe <hi>two Mites</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Treaſure</hi> of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>ſorrow,</hi> and to preſent, that now to your <hi>hands,</hi> which in my attendance in this woefull time J prouided for your <hi>hearts:</hi> They are <hi>plaine,</hi> both becauſe <hi>ſorrow</hi> diſlikes <hi>deſcant,</hi> and <hi>plaine</hi> ſtuffes are fitteſt for <hi>Mourners:</hi> they are <hi>paſſionate,</hi> for in my meditation <hi>by the riuers of ſorrow I ſat downe, &amp; wept, and hanged my Harpe vpon the willow,
<pb facs="tcp:15634:3"/>trees,</hi> for euer <hi>tuning</hi> it to <hi>comfort</hi> or <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody</hi> againe: and <hi>when</hi> ye required this <hi>ſong</hi> of mee in my <hi>heauineſſe,</hi> I knew not how to <hi>ſing</hi> any <hi>ſong of the Lord,</hi> but a ſong of <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> in this <hi>ſtrange land;</hi> ſtrange for the <hi>ſinnes,</hi> ſtrange for the iudgements. They are <hi>yours,</hi> they once breathed with you, and now euer ſhall <hi>liue</hi> with you, a pledge of that hart that neuer reioyced in any ſublunary <hi>obiect,</hi> more, then to ſee, while our <hi>Sunne</hi> did <hi>ſhine</hi> ſuch an happy, friendly <hi>aſpect</hi> of ſo many prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall <hi>Planets,</hi> and ſweet <hi>plants</hi> in this place: let <hi>Charity</hi> interpret me, and none will be <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended</hi> that vpon impetuous importunity I publiſh theſe laſt offices, to the memory of that <hi>illuſtrious Prince,</hi> our Maister, for whom the <hi>ſound</hi> of all <hi>tongues</hi> and applauſe of all hands teſtifie, neuer was any more <hi>honoured</hi> in his life, neuer any more <hi>lamented</hi> in his death, that euer beheld the light of <hi>heauen</hi> in this <hi>land.</hi> My beſt deuotion, &amp; faithfuleſt <hi>ſeruices</hi> are preſented with theſe; and ſo I remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all Chriſtian dutie</hi> Daniell Price.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15634:3"/>
            <head>The firſt Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 26.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>I will ſmite the Shepheard, and the Sheepe of the flocke ſhall be ſcattered.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Great Prince is falne in <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.38. 1 Sam. 4.21. Zach. 11.2. <hi>Auſt. de Paſ.</hi>
               </note> the ioy of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world is deceaſed, <hi>Ichabod,</hi> the glory of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is departed: Howle ye poore Firre Trees, your <hi>Cedar</hi> is fallen, <hi>Lachrimis non verbis, miſerationibus non orationibus opus eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know it is contrary to the <hi>grounds</hi> of <hi>Art,</hi> preſently, at the firſt entrance, to hoiſe vp ſayles in ſuch a ſea of <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation</hi> and <hi>ſorrow:</hi> But <hi>miſerie</hi> obſerues no rules of <hi>Oratory,</hi> and therefore without any further <hi>Proeme,</hi> wee ſhould all take vp that Elegy of <hi>Dauid,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.</note> 
               <hi>O noble Iſrael, he is ſlaine vpon thy high places! Tell it not in</hi> Gath, <hi>nor publiſh it in</hi> Aſcalon, <hi>leaſt the daughters of the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed reioyce. O ye Mountaines of</hi> Gilboa, <hi>vpon yee be neither dew nor raine, there the ſhield of the mighty was caſt downe:</hi> Ionathan <hi>was lonely and pleaſant in his life, ſwift as an Eagle, ſtrong as a Lyon: ye ſonnes of Iſrael weepe for</hi> Ionathan, <hi>which clothed you in Scarlet, with pleaſures, and hanged ornaments of Gold vpon your apparell.</hi> All of you of what condition ſoeuer, heare with <hi>ſilence</hi> what you feele with <hi>ſorrow,</hi> the very thunderbolt of heauen. <hi>I will ſmite the Shepheard, and the ſheepe of the flocke ſhall be ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15634:4"/>
               <hi>Take vp a lamentation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem.</note> ſayth the Lord to the Prophet, <hi>A lamentation ſuch as was not in the daies of our fathers.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, no lamentation will ſit our loſſe, a <hi>deluge</hi> of <hi>teares</hi> is little enough to beare the <hi>arke</hi> of our <hi>ſorrow. Austin</hi> is ſayd to weepe a <hi>ſhoure</hi> of <hi>teares, Ambroſe</hi> a <hi>flood</hi> of <hi>tears;</hi> but you will tell me,<note place="margin">Doct. Swale</note> 
               <hi>Rhetorie intur Patres:</hi> I am ſure <hi>Ieremy</hi> wiſhed for a fountaine of teares, and my <hi>ſorrowing</hi> &amp; <hi>louing brother</hi> hath brought you a Saboath dayes iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney towards this <hi>Fountaine,</hi> him I follow with paces of <hi>lamentation</hi> and <hi>loue,</hi> and with as faithfull as ſorrowfull obſeruance, to his memory, for whom we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to continue theſe our laſt accompliſhments of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance: we ſhall both endeuor to teach you that laſt leſſon of our Sauiour, <hi>Weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelues.</hi> I haue at this time ſetled the foundation of my meditations vpon the <hi>farewell of Chriſt</hi> to his Diſciples. A prophecy found in <hi>Zachary</hi> 400. yeeres before it was vſed heere;<note place="margin">Zach 13.7. Mark. 14.28. Ioh. 16.27</note> repeated in <hi>Matthew,</hi> in <hi>Mark,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> in all theſe places prophecying of the death of the lord of life. <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> is a true <hi>Phariſie,</hi> but <hi>griefe</hi> is a bad <hi>Scribe,</hi> expect neither order nor matter, ſorrow hath deuided ſuch ſhares among vs, the ſcattered ſheepe and flocke of this fold, that our ſoules are euen deuided within vs.</p>
            <p>The words themſelues, without any deſcant, be words of <hi>amazement</hi> and <hi>aſtoniſhment, I will ſmite the ſhepherd, and the ſheepe of the flocke ſhall be ſcattered.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.16 Ier. 23.29. Heb. 4.12. Eph. 6.17.</note> Euery word of the Lord is a <hi>power,</hi> a <hi>fire,</hi> a <hi>hammer,</hi> a <hi>Pyoner,</hi> to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw ſtrong holds, a <hi>ſword</hi> to deuide the reynes and the marrow. But this an extraordinary word, it is the <hi>alarum</hi> to a battel, the voice of a <hi>Trumpet,</hi> an Earthquake, ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Pillars of the Earth, <hi>I will ſmite the ſhepheard, and the ſheep ſhall be ſcattered.</hi> I will ſmite, <hi>vox furoris &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loris,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15634:4"/>ſayth a <hi>Gloſse,</hi> the voyce of fury in God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gloſſ. Bern.</hi> Leu. 27. Deut. 28. Reu. 3.19.</note> the voyce of miſery to man. It had beene more milde, if, as in <hi>Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> I will puniſh: or in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> I will correct: or in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> I will chaſtiſe. But who is able to beare his blow? who is able to ſtand before him if he be angry? by the leaſt of his blowes wee are cut downe, dryed vp, and withered.</p>
            <p>I will ſmite the <hi>Shepheard,</hi> not the <hi>ſheepe</hi> of his Paſture, not the <hi>Ewes</hi> great with yong, not the <hi>Lambes</hi> of the Fold: if the <hi>ſheepe</hi> onely had bin ſmitten,<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids</hi> prayer had ſerued; how long wilt thou proceed in anger againſt the ſheep of this paſture? But the ſtroke is greater, more grieuous, it is falne vpon the ſhepheard, the guider, the glory, the Prince of the people: <hi>I will ſmite the ſhepheard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered:</hi> his poore followers haue no better phraſe then the ſheepe of his flocke, ſilly, ſimple, innocent creatures: Wolues haue <hi>dens,</hi> Foxes <hi>holes,</hi> Birds of the heauen <hi>neſts;</hi> but Sheepe wander out of the way in the <hi>wilderneſſe, Errant in montibus agni,</hi> they haue no Citie to dwell in. If the ſeruants of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour</hi> had no more miſery then they may collect out of the condition and conſideration of being called <hi>ſheep,</hi> it is much. Poore creatures, when they are ſtrongeſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue no meanes to withſtand the incurſions &amp; inuaſions of the <hi>Wolues;</hi> but the Text ſtirreth vp more ſenſe of <hi>ſorrow: The ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be ſcattered:</hi> it were, as if they were <hi>ſcattered</hi> &amp; <hi>conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med:</hi> Be <hi>diſperſed,</hi> it is as if they were deſtroyed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lorinus.</hi> Pſal. 119.</note> 
               <hi>di-ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere</hi> is <hi>biſ-perdere:</hi> they ſhal be, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh, either gone aſtray, like the ſheep that periſhed, or as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, as <hi>ſheepe prouided for the ſlaughter.</hi> Scattered they muſt be: <hi>I wil ſmite the ſhepherd, &amp; the ſtocke ſhalbe ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:15634:5"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diuiſio. </seg>
               </label> The <hi>parts</hi> are two: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>1</label> firſt, the <hi>death</hi> of the <hi>Shepheard:</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the <hi>diſperſion</hi> of the <hi>ſheepe.</hi> The death of the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, plainely in theſe words, <hi>I will ſmite the Shepheard:</hi> wherein, becauſe I will not trouble you with vnneceſſary fractions: Looke vpon, firſt, <hi>The perſon</hi> ſmiting, I will <hi>ſmite:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>The perſon</hi> ſmitten, I will ſmite the <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard.</hi> Secondly, in the <hi>diſperſion</hi> of the <hi>ſheepe,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>and the ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered,</hi> obſerue, firſt, the <hi>denomination</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Seruants,</hi> The ſheepe: ſecondly, the <hi>deſolation</hi> of theſe <hi>ſheep,</hi> The ſheep ſhall be ſcattered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will ſmite.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen.</note> 
               <hi>Non niſi coact us percuitis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> it is neither the <hi>Nature</hi> nor <hi>pleaſure</hi> of God to be ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. <hi>Abaddon, Apolluon,</hi> be the names of <hi>Sathan</hi> in the <hi>Reuelation:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuelat.</note> but the <hi>Lord is a gratious God and mercifull, ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſſe, &amp; repenteth him of the euill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gloſſ. Ord.</hi> Ioel 2. Exod. 34.6.</note> 
               <hi>Benignus affectu, miſericors effectu, ſaith the Gloſſe vpon the ſecond of Ioel: Moſes</hi> in the thundring and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heard no other attributes vpon the Mount: <hi>Dauid</hi> in his ſorrowes acknowledged no other: <hi>Ionas</hi> in the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Whale, &amp; bottome of hel, among all the waues and ſurges, remembreth no other: <hi>Ioel</hi> in his day of darkeneſſe, and blackneſſe, repeateth no other affections of the Lord,<note place="margin">Ioel 2.</note> but theſe, <hi>the Lord is gracious and mercifull, ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſſe, &amp; repenteth him of the euil.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.</note> The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> giues God theſe titles, the <hi>Lord is ſtrong and patient,</hi> there is hony in the <hi>Lyon,</hi> ſweetneſſe in <hi>ſtrength,</hi> he is not onely <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>patient,</hi> but <hi>ſtrong in patience,</hi> he doth foreſlow his <hi>vials,</hi> and forbeare his <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> till the <hi>cart-roapes</hi> of <hi>ſinne</hi> doe hurry downe his <hi>iudgements.</hi> It may be he will vpon long expectation cut away the <hi>lappe</hi> of our <hi>garment,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> did by <hi>Saul,</hi> but it is a rare example, that hee proceedeth againſtany, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15634:5"/>Satans motion was againſt <hi>Iob,</hi> to <hi>ſtretch out his hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1.11. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; touch all that he had.</hi> There were foure ages of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in all foure the people continued ſinfull: the iudgements expected were fearefull. In the firſt age of the <hi>Patriarkes,</hi> he promiſed a bleſſing to their poſteritie: in the ſecond age, of <hi>Iudges,</hi> he ſetled their Common-wealth and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy in the third age, of <hi>Kings,</hi> he built them a Citie to dwell in: in the fourth, of <hi>Prophets,</hi> he built them a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to pray in: hee might haue blaſted them in their <hi>Spring,</hi> but he ſuffereth them to come to their <hi>Autumne;</hi> nay further, hee endured them till their owne looſeneſſe brought them to the <hi>fall of the leafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the moſt <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>baſe</hi> condition of man, that when as God hath no other <hi>Fountaine</hi> then the fountaine of Grace in <hi>Zachary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 4.</note> nor other <hi>riches</hi> then the riches of his mercy in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> nor other <hi>bowels</hi> then the bowels of compaſſion, and that the vnlimited extent of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>affection</hi> is beyond all imaginable proportions, yet notwithſtanding, <hi>man</hi> will vnſheath Gods ſword, &amp; will violently force him to his <hi>armory,</hi> to put on his <hi>habergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>brigandine,</hi> as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh; to whet his <hi>ſword,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 59.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to bend his <hi>Bow,</hi> and to prouide him <hi>deadly weapons,</hi> to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine his <hi>arrowes</hi> againſt them that perſecute him, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> threatneth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.13.</note> that Heauen ſhall afford milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Angels;</hi> Hell, legions of wicked <hi>ſpirits; Orbs,</hi> and <hi>Arches</hi> of Heauen, Stars to fight in their order; <hi>Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> regions, Haile, Froſt, Snowe, Stormes, Tempeſts, Mildew, Blaſtings: and the earth his great artillery-yard, to ſend out Lice, Mice, Flyes, Wormes, the very Niſſets, Palmerwormes, Locuſts, Caterpillers, Cankerwormes, <hi>ſmall creatures,</hi> yet great <hi>armies,</hi> as he calleth them in <hi>Ioel:</hi> hereby cauſing <hi>Iordan</hi> to runne backe,<note place="margin">Ioel 2.25.</note> his mercy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15634:6"/>to retire, yea, conſtrayning him to alter his owne deſire and nature, and tenor of ſpeech, as in this place, <hi>I will ſmite;</hi> &amp; not onely ſo, but as <hi>before,</hi> they cauſe the ſtroke, ſo <hi>afterwards</hi> they neglect the ſtroke,<note place="margin">Pliny.</note> as if the iudgements of God were like to thoſe <hi>Bruta fulmina</hi> among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> which, becauſe they fell vpon the beaſtes, neuer came to obſeruation. So wicked and beaſtly men neuer obſerue, neither <hi>why</hi> hee ſtriketh, nor <hi>who</hi> it is that ſtriketh. A <hi>father</hi> hath no ioy in the continuall chiding or ſcourging, or curſing of his ſonne, nay, his very bowels yearne within him for ſorrow, his affection can be no leſſe,<note place="margin">Prou. 31.1.</note> then of the mother of <hi>Lemuel, O my ſonne, O the ſon of my wombe, O the ſonne of my deſires.</hi> The <hi>compaſsion</hi> of the Lord can be no leſſe, whoſe mercies be aboue all his works: yet, if a man will not turne, he will whet <hi>his ſword,</hi> and bend <hi>his bow:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Pſal. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>acerbitatem poenae gladius, celeritatem deſignat arcus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome:</hi> In vaine doe any attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the inuentions of <hi>ſwords</hi> to the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>7.</hi> Nat. Hiſtor. Ludolph.</note> or of <hi>bowes,</hi> to the <hi>Scrythians,</hi> God hath prepared them, <hi>eius ſunt arma, cuius ſunt verba, ego percutiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeruation. </seg>Firſt</label> The <hi>obſeruation</hi> collected from the words <hi>I will ſmite,</hi> is this, <hi>that in all iudgements we ought truly to iudge of the true author:</hi> he that being asked his name by <hi>Moſes,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>I am that I am;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.14</note> he it is that afterwards threatens, I will bring <hi>famine;</hi> I will bring the <hi>ſword;</hi> I will bring the <hi>peſtilence.</hi> In the ten plagues of <hi>Egipt;</hi> in the beginning of them his words be, <hi>In this thou ſhalt know that I am the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 7.17 Exod. 15.3</note> 
               <hi>I will ſmite.</hi> He is a <hi>man of War,</hi> in the ſame booke: Nay, <hi>the Lord of hoſts and armies,</hi> often called in his own booke: <hi>Murraine of cattell</hi> is called his hand; <hi>Pestilence</hi> his ſword;<note place="margin">Exod. 9.3. 1 Chro. 21 Pſal. 91.</note> 
               <hi>ſickneſſes</hi> his arrowes; his <hi>bow</hi> hangeth in the <hi>cloud;</hi> his <hi>ſword</hi> is euer in his hand; his <hi>axes</hi> &amp; <hi>hammers</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15634:6"/>be in readines; he it is that doth <hi>hurt</hi> and <hi>ſhoot,</hi> &amp; <hi>wound</hi> and <hi>ſtrike,</hi> and <hi>ſpoile</hi> and <hi>ouerturne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom. Odyſ.</note> He is not <hi>Iupiter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ermis,</hi> as one thought, but as another ſpake, his weapons be innumerable, &amp; his hands vnreſiſtable. The religious Saints of God acknowledged this; <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhal ſpeake for all. <hi>O Lord, thy anger, thy heauy diſpleaſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note> 
               <hi>thy arrowes ſticke faſt in me, thy hand preſſeth downe ſore.</hi> The rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> acknowledged this when <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> as we finde in the old Teſtament, had bin 7. times aſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; by <hi>Shiſhak</hi> King of <hi>Egipt</hi> in <hi>Rehoboams</hi> dayes;<note place="margin">1 Kin. 14. 2 Chro. 25 23. Iſa. 7.1. 2 Kin. 18. 2 Chro. 33 2 Kin. 33. 2 Kin. 25.</note> by <hi>Ioas</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Amaziahs</hi> time; by <hi>Rezin</hi> King of <hi>Aram</hi> in the raigne of <hi>Ahaz;</hi> by <hi>Zenacherib</hi> King of <hi>Aſhur</hi> in the time of <hi>Hezekias;</hi> by the captaines of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> who tooke <hi>Manaſſes</hi> captiue; by <hi>Pharaoh Necho,</hi> that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away <hi>Iehoas</hi> priſoner; laſtly, by the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> who burnt the Temple, and defaced the Citie: and that they had enemies round about them; on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> the <hi>Moabits Ammorites, Aſſyrians;</hi> on the <hi>weſt</hi> ſide, the <hi>Philistines;</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> the <hi>Syrians,</hi> on the <hi>South</hi> the <hi>Aegiptians, Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians,</hi> and <hi>Idumeans,</hi> all moſt infeſtuous to them, yet ſtill cry out in their vexations vnto God; <hi>thou haſt couered vs with wrath, thou haſt made vs the off-ſcouring of the people.</hi> Nay, <hi>ſuperſtitious heathens</hi> haue acknowledged this:<note place="margin">Lam. 2.43 Exo. 8.19.</note> the <hi>Enchanters,</hi> that the plague of Lice was the finger of God: <hi>Tiberius,</hi> that Thunder was the power of God: <hi>Homer,</hi> that the plague was the arrow of God:<note place="margin">Hip. in prog.</note> 
               <hi>Hypocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> that a great plague among them, was a puniſhment ſent from God. Nay, <hi>blaſphemous reprobates</hi> haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed this; for the <hi>damned,</hi> at what time the ſtorme fell vpon them in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> they blaſphemed God,<note place="margin">Reu. 16.24.</note> becauſe of that plague of <hi>Haile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> A <hi>doctrine</hi> to confute thoſe that put the iudgements
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15634:7"/>of <hi>God</hi> farre from themſelues, by putting them far from the true author of them, God himſelfe. <hi>Naturall</hi> &amp; <hi>beaſtly</hi> men, who make naturall cauſes the reaſons of ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall euents, who to the <hi>wantonneſſe</hi> of <hi>wit,</hi> adde <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of <hi>will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73 9.</note> and belike to thoſe ſpoke of in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> that talke preſumptuouſly, and ſet their mouth againſt Heauen, making the power of God to be circumſcribed by the power of reaſon, who, becauſe they beleeue no more then they ſee, and feare no more then they feele, they goe no further then the <hi>preſence,</hi> neuer goe into the <hi>priuy</hi>-chamber of Gods iudgements, ſecond cauſes muſt remoue it from the firſt author. But I aske, as the Apoſtle doth, <hi>O thou man, who art thou that diſputeſt with God?</hi> or rather, who art thou that denieſt the prerogatiue of God? ſeeing he hath ſayd, I doe ſtrike; I will ſmite.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
               </label> In this our <hi>incomparable loſſe</hi> (of which though I ſhall neuer <hi>thinke</hi> or <hi>ſpeake</hi> without an indiuidual companion, <hi>ſorrow,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſorrow</hi> attended with the vtmoſt <hi>remembrance</hi> and <hi>reuerence</hi> limited vnder heauen) I may vrge this one part of my Text vnto them who neuer looking vp to heauens vnreſiſtable ſtroke, doe complaine that eyther the want of care, or skill in the Phiſitians, ſhipwrackt all our hope in that bleſſed <hi>Arke</hi> the Prince.</p>
            <p>I ſtand not heere to <hi>dawbe,</hi> with vntempered Morter, neither to feare, nor flatter any; I doe beleeue that they were both <hi>ſorrowfull</hi> beholders, and <hi>faithfull</hi> helpers, ſo far as <hi>Art, Vigilance,</hi> and <hi>diligence,</hi> could extend. But when <hi>ego percutiam</hi> is once proclaimed, no Phiſitian can cure <hi>Aſa</hi> his legs, or lay a <hi>plaiſter</hi> vnto <hi>Fzekias</hi> botch, or cure the <hi>Shunamites</hi> child, crying, my <hi>head.</hi> No balme in <hi>Gilead</hi> can help the <hi>feuers, dropſies</hi> or <hi>bloody iſsues,</hi> which Chriſt healed, though the <hi>patient Patients</hi> beſtowal they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15634:7"/>haue vpon thoſe honorable inſtruments; for ſo the ſon of <hi>Syrach</hi> calleth Phiſitians. And therefore as thoſe, in the Prophet cryed, a <hi>Conſpiracie,</hi> a <hi>Conſpiracie;</hi> ſo theſe, <hi>Poyſon, Poyſon:</hi> How probable ſoeuer that may be; let them looke vnto the poyſon of their owne ſoules, the onely <hi>infection</hi> that brought this heauy <hi>affliction</hi> vpon vs. And whatſoeuer ſecond cauſes there might be, let vs leaue the conſideration thereof to them, to whom they belong: and let vs (which doth only concerne our ſelues) with feare and reuerence, and humilitie, confeſſe it was Gods hand,<note place="margin">Greg. Mar. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> as both <hi>Gregorie</hi> confeſſeth vpon the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Iob,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ambroſe</hi> before him of all ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: <hi>Cum Diabolus vulnerat, Domini ſunt ſagittae:</hi> Whatſoeuer the ſecond cauſes be, yet the ſupreme rule of all is in Gods hand.</p>
            <p>But while I am thus informing others, my owne ſoule becomes a <hi>ſceptick,</hi> and queſtions thus: <hi>Could God forget to be gratious?</hi> would he in diſpleaſure ſo ſmite Him, that was our ioy &amp; hope? Yes, that he might more fully ſettle our hope vpon the true <hi>obiect,</hi> God himſelfe. But would he, ſo ſmite as to take him away in the Sunne-ſhine of his time? yes, that he might beſtow farre greater brightneſſe vpon him. <hi>Alas,</hi> he was in the <hi>flower</hi> and <hi>ſplendor</hi> of his youth: he was leſſe <hi>taynted,</hi> leſſe <hi>blemiſhed.</hi> His <hi>death</hi> was the vndoing of many his poore <hi>ſeruants:</hi> but <hi>God</hi> is able to prouide for them better then he could:<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Let them truſt in the Lord, and verily they ſhall be fed.</hi> He was taken away in this <hi>ſolemne expectation</hi> of <hi>Nuptiall-ioy</hi> and <hi>triumph:</hi> He is gone to greater ioy, to <hi>the Marriage of the Lambe;</hi> to thoſe ioyes, triumphs, Angels Quire &amp; Songs, to which no burden, nor no end belongs. He was taken away, as it were ſomewhat ſodainly, and vnexpectedly; yet not ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15634:8"/>ſodainely as the <hi>fiery enemies</hi> of God and the King enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that <hi>furious ſulphureous</hi> plot to haue blowne him vp:<note place="margin">2 King. 23.</note> neither ſo ſodainely as <hi>Ioſias</hi> the <hi>dearling of God,</hi> who had no more warning then while an arrow made a <hi>doore</hi> in his <hi>breaſt</hi> for <hi>Death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 35.20.</note> But our <hi>Ioſias</hi> was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in a ſeaſonable, comfortable viſitation, when he was full of <hi>beautie,</hi> full of <hi>glory,</hi> full of <hi>pietie,</hi> full of <hi>Religion,</hi> full of <hi>admiration,</hi> full of <hi>lamentation.</hi> Beloued, in a word, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh; <hi>Comfort your ſelues, one another, with theſe words:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1. Ionas 2.</note> The <hi>Lord</hi> gaue him, and the <hi>Lord</hi> hath taken him: and as <hi>Ionas</hi> Marriners acknowledge; Thou O Lord haſt done as it pleaſed thee.</p>
            <p>(As it followeth) <hi>Thou haſt ſmitten the Shepheard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Cir. </seg>2</label> To haue ſmit a <hi>Wolfe,</hi> deuouring the <hi>ſheepe,</hi> had bin <hi>mercy;</hi> to haue ſmitten one <hi>ſheepe</hi> of the fold had bin <hi>iudgement</hi> with <hi>mercy,</hi> but to ſmite the <hi>ſhepheard</hi> may ſeeme <hi>iudgement</hi> and <hi>fury.</hi> In this <hi>houre</hi> &amp; <hi>time</hi> of <hi>mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> now we ſit as in the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of <hi>death;</hi> it is fitter for you to feed on the <hi>tree of life,</hi> then on the <hi>tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> &amp; therefore I deſire to confine my ſpeech only vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>meditation;</hi> but the word <hi>ſhepheard</hi> leades me forth further then I thought, beſides the waters of <hi>comfort.</hi> A ſhepheard was the firſt <hi>tradeſman;</hi> though the ſecond ſon of all the children of <hi>Adam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.2.</note> and after <hi>Abel</hi> many <hi>ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards</hi> were in neer attendance vpon <hi>God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypri. ſerm. de Nat. Chri.</note> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath collected them, and hath the Catalogue of them. <hi>Abel Paſtor outum fuit, fuerunt et Patriarchae paſtores, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum tandem familiarum principes; Paſtor fuit Moſes; Paſtor Dauid, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the beginning after the creation, in the olde <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> God choſe <hi>ſhepherds</hi> to be his <hi>ſeruants.</hi> In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the time of redemption, in the new <hi>Teſtament,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15634:8"/>Chriſt choſe <hi>fiſhers</hi> to be his <hi>diſciples: ſhepherds</hi> haue a ſolitary life; <hi>fiſhermen</hi> a watry life. In ſhepherds the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents haue hierogkiphically obſerued <hi>contemplation,</hi> in fiſhermen <hi>lamentation.</hi> A ſhepherds life, ſaith <hi>Philo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de vit. Moiſ.</note> is <hi>praeludium ad regnum;</hi> of which phraſe <hi>Homer</hi> and other Grecians haue made vſe: and the old Teſtament hath none of more eſteeme then ſhepherds. <hi>Moſes,</hi> that kept <hi>Iethro</hi> his ſheepe; <hi>Iacob,</hi> that kept <hi>Labans</hi> ſheepe; <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was ſent to <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſheepe; <hi>Amos</hi> a Prophet, taken from the <hi>heard; Moſes</hi> a Prieſt and Prophet, from the ſheepe; <hi>Dauid,</hi> the Lords ſouldier, and whoeuer had ſuch victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as <hi>Dauid?</hi> taken from the fold; <hi>Elias,</hi> the Lords Seer, and you know what the ſpirit of <hi>Elias</hi> was, yet he taken from the <hi>cattell.</hi> But more then this, <hi>God the Father</hi> is called a ſhepherd in the Pſalmes;<note place="margin">Pſal. 80.1. Ioh. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>O thou ſhepherd of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, thou that leadeſt</hi> Ioſeph <hi>like a ſheepe. God the Son</hi> doth name himſelfe a <hi>ſhepheard</hi> in the Goſpell: <hi>God the holy Spirit,</hi> is named a <hi>ſhepheard</hi> in <hi>Peter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.</note> the Shepheard and Biſhop of our ſoules. I haue lead you ſo farre, onely to ſhew in what <hi>honor</hi> the name, function, perſon of ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards haue beene: you may the more wonder at the words <hi>percutiam Paſtore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Abel</hi> the firſt ſhepherd may be <hi>ſlaughtered;</hi> but this ſhepherd, by excellencie called the ſhepherd, he that is <hi>bonus Paſtor, magnus paſtor, Princeps Paſtorum. Formoſi pecoris cuſtos, &amp;c. He that was white and ruddy, the faireſt of ten thouſand; full of grace were his lips; ſpetioſus ſuae filijs hominum: he whoſe head was fine as gold, whoſe lockes were curled, who had cheekes as a bed of ſpices, lips like lillies, hands as rings of Cryſolites, legges as pillars of marble, whoſe countenance was as Lebanon, whoſe mouth as ſweete things; who was wholly delectable: O my God; is he ſtriken? yes, and ſmitten with ſuch a deadly blow,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15634:9"/>that the Axeliree of heauen could not haue born it. Eſay</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, <hi>vir dolorum,</hi> and <hi>Ieremy</hi> expreſſeth his inexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible griefe, <hi>dolor non ſicut dolor,</hi> neuer ſorrow like his ſorrow. Sorrow followed him from his birth to his buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. In his <hi>birth</hi> perſecuted by <hi>Tyrants;</hi> in his <hi>life</hi> tempted by <hi>diuels;</hi> at his <hi>death</hi> apprehended by <hi>Traytors;</hi> ſcourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; ſpitte vpon by <hi>ſouldiers; vile fied</hi> more then a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer; crucified with <hi>Theeues;</hi> a <hi>Croſſe,</hi> the curſe of the Law, to beare him, and he to beare all the ſinnes of the world; his moſt bleſſed body to be <hi>mangled</hi> and <hi>goared,</hi> his ſoule to drinke vp ſorrow, &amp; thus to giue vp the <hi>ghoſt. Paſtor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pellican.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtus, dilectus filius, Populi, Doctor, ſuper hunc excitantur perſecutorum manus: vpon Chriſt,</hi> who was <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenitus,</hi> nay, <hi>vnigenitus,</hi> the beloued ſon, the Doctor of his people, the Shepheard of his ſheepe, the <hi>Lambe</hi> of God, the <hi>Lyon</hi> of Iuda, the expreſſe <hi>Character</hi> of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the <hi>light</hi> of the Gentiles, <hi>glory</hi> of his people <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the <hi>hands</hi> of his perſecutors are lifted vp, and fall downe with this <hi>heauy, heauy</hi> blow.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label> The <hi>obſeruation</hi> hence is, <hi>that the great height of ſinnes, bring downe ſo heauy weight of iudgements, as that God will not ſpare his owne onely one, his deare one, his faire one, his Son Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> I ſay no more <hi>in this,</hi> but what <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> gathereth from that of <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. in Eſay.</note> 
               <hi>Propt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r ſcelus populi mei percuſsi eum:</hi> for <hi>ſin</hi> he was ſmitten, who had no <hi>ſin;</hi> and the <hi>blow was ſo heauy that the mountaines trembled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not onely was <hi>Chriſt</hi> taken away for ſin, but in fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods wrath, hee often giues the world ſuch a <hi>ſhocke</hi> and <hi>ſtroke</hi> that it reeles, and almoſt ouerwhelmes, with the dart of vengeance that ſtrikes into the heart of a <hi>kingdome,</hi> by taking away the <hi>choſen</hi> ſeruants of God, the choſen ſhepheards of the world, ſuch as are <hi>Kings</hi> &amp;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15634:9"/>
               <hi>Princes,</hi> who as <hi>Chriſt</hi> communicated of mans miſerie, ſo theſe participate of Gods Maieſtie: &amp; yet in his furie he will ſmite theſe. Witneſſe <hi>Ioſias</hi> the dearling of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>apple</hi> of his eye, the <hi>ſignet</hi> on his right hand; <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied</hi> of three hundred yeeres before his birth: <hi>lamented</hi> among the poſteritie of the <hi>Iewes</hi> after his death: yet <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> muſt be ſmitten; <hi>Ioſias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 49.</note> whoſe remembrance <hi>is like the perfume that is made by the Apothecary, ſweet as hony in all mouthes, and as muſicke at a banquet of wine; he that was a patterne of reformation to all ſucceeding Princes:</hi> yet <hi>Ioſias</hi> muſt be ſmitten; he that deſtroyed the idolatrous <hi>Prieſts,</hi> &amp; <hi>monuments</hi> of <hi>Baal,</hi> the Sunne, Moone, Planets with all their high Places, or Valleyes, or Groues, or Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, or Veſſels, and cut downe, burnt to aſhes, beate to powder, threw into the brooke, and left no ſigne of them: yet <hi>Ioſias</hi> muſt be ſmitten:<note place="margin">2 King. 23. 2 Chro. 35</note> 
               <hi>Ioſias</hi> whoſe <hi>Epipoheneme</hi> and <hi>acclamation</hi> was; like vnto him was no King before him; whoſe <hi>Elegy</hi> and <hi>Lamentation</hi> was ſuch as neuer the like before or after him; all ſinging men and ſinging women lament him to his day, and neuer the like mourning as that of <hi>Hadadrimmon</hi> in the valley of <hi>Megiddo;</hi> yet <hi>Ioſias</hi> muſt be ſmitten. <hi>Non ſimilis,</hi> for his honorable reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Non ſimilis,</hi> for his memorable lamentation, <hi>yet</hi> the right hand of the Almighty ſpared not <hi>Ioſias.</hi> In the <hi>Chronicles</hi> of all the Kings, from <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining <hi>fourteene</hi> generations and <hi>forty</hi> Kings, there was not one that gaue or tooke the like <hi>example of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For as among the bad, <hi>Rehoboam</hi> did ill, <hi>Ieroboam</hi> worſe, <hi>Omri</hi> worſe then he, <hi>Ahab</hi> worſe then all; ſo on the contrary, though <hi>Aſa</hi> did right in the eyes of the lord,<note place="margin">1 King. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; his ſon <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> walked in the wayes of <hi>Aſa</hi> his father. <hi>Amaſiah</hi> did vprightly in the ſight of the Lord,<note place="margin">1 King. 22</note> and <hi>Aza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15634:10"/>his ſon did according to all that his father <hi>Amaſiah</hi> did.<note place="margin">2 King. 14</note>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 15</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> was a man after Gods owne heart, &amp; <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne for his wiſedome, honor, riches and happines, exceeded his father <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 10</note> yet euery one of theſe had ſome ſcarre, ſome blots, ſome blemiſhes, an <hi>eclipticke line</hi> ranne through each of their <hi>Zodiackes;</hi> onely <hi>Ioſias</hi> is without any noted ſpot or wrinckle; like him was no king before him. What then was the reaſon that this Roſe of the <hi>garland</hi> muſt be blaſted; the diamond of the <hi>Crowne</hi> be darkened; the Paragon of all the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah</hi> muſt be ſmitten; that <hi>percutiam,</hi> the word of my Text, ſerued his <hi>execution</hi> ſo violently vpon <hi>Ioſias?</hi> Why would he that breaketh the <hi>bow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> knappeth the <hi>ſpeare</hi> in ſunder, &amp; caſteth the <hi>arrowes</hi> in the fire, I ſay, why would he let the <hi>Archers</hi> ſhoot at King <hi>Ioſias?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 22</note> It was the <hi>voyce</hi> of the King of <hi>Aram</hi> to his Captaines, concerning wicked King <hi>Ahab, fight ye neither againſt great nor ſmall, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King;</hi> but that the Lord ſhould direct that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall <hi>arrow</hi> to be the death of his darling <hi>Ioſias,</hi> this <hi>arrow</hi> ſtrikes vs with admiration. I cannot but beare part with thoſe mourners in <hi>Megiddo; Alas</hi> for this great day, <hi>Alas</hi> for that good Prince, <hi>Alas</hi> that <hi>Ioſias</hi> is ſmitten.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Dauid</hi> numbred the people, the people dyed, they ſuffered for his ſinne,<note place="margin">1 Chro. 21</note> 
               <hi>plectuntur Achiui;</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> cryeth, <hi>What haue they done? it is euen I that haue ſinned, Is it not I that haue commanded to number the people? but theſe ſheepe what haue they done? O Lord my God, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, let thine hand be on me, and on my fathers houſe, and not on thy people for their deſtruction.</hi> There the <hi>people</hi> were plagued for the offence of the <hi>Prince,</hi> but heere the <hi>Prince</hi> is ſmitten for the offence of the <hi>people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I finde eſpecially <hi>two cauſes</hi> why <hi>Ioſias</hi> was ſmitten.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15634:10"/>Firſt, for the ſinnes of the time:<note place="margin">The firſt cauſe of the death of <hi>Ioſias.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>ſinnes</hi> of thoſe dayes I collect out of <hi>Zephany,</hi> to be <hi>ſtrange</hi> and <hi>horride.</hi> In the <hi>front</hi> of the <hi>Prophecie</hi> you may ſee that he propheſied in the dayes of <hi>Ioſias:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.1.</note> in the ſecond verſe of that Chapter there is a fearefull deſtruction pronounced; ſuch as in ſo few wordes, is not to be found in all the <hi>Prophets.</hi> It is a generall <hi>obſeruation,</hi> that where we heare ſome ſtrange <hi>deſolation</hi> threatned, there is ſome ſtrange <hi>abhomination</hi> committed. Obſerue both here: firſt the <hi>deſolation</hi> thret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; <hi>I will ſurely deſtroy all things from the Land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.1.2</note> ſaith the Lord: <hi>I will deſtroy man and beaſt; I will deſtroy the fowles of the heauen, and the fiſhes of the ſea, and ruines ſhall be to the wicked, and I will cut off man from the land,</hi> ſaith the Lord, &amp;c. It is ſo terrible, as if that in the <hi>Pſalm</hi> were fulfilled, <hi>Deſtructions are come to a perpetuall end:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 9.</note> a <hi>deluge</hi> and <hi>Catacliſme,</hi> a <hi>deuaſtation</hi> &amp; <hi>deſolation vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable.</hi> The greateſt <hi>plagues</hi> that euer came on the world were either the <hi>particular,</hi> in the Iudgements on <hi>Egipt;</hi> or the <hi>generall,</hi> in the drowning of the <hi>World.</hi> In <hi>Egipt,</hi> beſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>flyes,</hi> and <hi>lice,</hi> and <hi>frogs,</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> there was the <hi>killing of the firſt-borne, Murraine of Beaſts, death of Fiſhes, by the water turned into bloud;</hi> but I find no where that their <hi>fowle</hi> of heauen were deſtroyed: In the <hi>drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of the World, <hi>all mankinde was not deſtroyed, eight Soules were preſerued,</hi> and although the <hi>beaſts</hi> of the <hi>field,</hi> and <hi>fowles</hi> of the <hi>ayre</hi> periſhed, yet I can no way collect the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>fiſhes;</hi> thoſe watry <hi>creatures</hi> kept their <hi>Colonyes.</hi> In <hi>Egipt, beaſts</hi> and <hi>fiſhes</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, not the <hi>fowles:</hi> In the <hi>floud, beaſts</hi> and <hi>fowles,</hi> not the <hi>fiſhes;</hi> but in this, <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Beaſt, Fiſh</hi> and <hi>Fowle,</hi> all things threatned to be deſtroyed from the earth. Secondly therefore conſider the <hi>abhomination</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15634:11"/>in thoſe times; you may at firſt ſight collect them out of the following verſes. In the 4. verſe,<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.4.1.</note> there was a <hi>remnant</hi> of <hi>Baall</hi> in the land, reſembling our <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Chemarims,</hi> fit parallels to our <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>5</label> Thirdly, in the 5. verſe, there were <hi>ſome that ſware by the Lord, and ſware by Malcham,</hi> equalling the <hi>falſe-harted, halfe hollow-harted</hi> Hipocrites of two <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions</hi> in theſe dayes. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>6</label> Fourthly, in the 6. verſe, <hi>ſome that turned backe from the Lord,</hi> like to our <hi>Ephraimitall A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postaticall</hi> reuolters. Fiftly, <hi>ſome that ſought not the Lord, nor inquired after him,</hi> ſhadowing the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> of our land. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>8</label> Sixtly, in the 8. verſe, ſuch as were cloathed with <hi>ſtrange apparell,</hi> the characters of the <hi>guls</hi> and <hi>gallants</hi> of our dayes. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>9</label> In the 9. verſe, ſome that <hi>daunced</hi> vpon the <hi>threſhold</hi> ſo proudly; the note of the quaint <hi>Crane-paced</hi> Courtiers of this time. Laſtly, thoſe that filled <hi>houſes</hi> by <hi>cruelty</hi> and <hi>deceit;</hi> the brand of the ſinfull and couetous <hi>Citizens</hi> of this Citie. Now meaſure with the <hi>cubit</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> whether <hi>deſolation</hi> be not fitted to <hi>abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi> Runne to and fro through the ſtreete of that Chapter, and ſee, and heare, and feare, and tremble: Sinnes were the cauſe of that threatned <hi>deſtruction,</hi> ſinnes were the <hi>Cart-ropes, Engines, Pioners,</hi> the <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, Whirlewindes, Thunderbolts,</hi> finall <hi>downefall</hi> and <hi>funerall,</hi> and <hi>deuaſtation</hi> of that State.</p>
            <p>In the time of the <hi>Iudges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 20.44.</note> the Lord almoſt extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the Tribe of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> eighteen thouſand at one time.<note place="margin">1 King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> In the time of the <hi>Kings</hi> ten Tribes fell from <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell.</hi> But this miſery is more; <hi>Roote</hi> and <hi>Branch, head</hi> and <hi>tayle,</hi> as the Prophet ſore-told, <hi>Man, Beaſt, Fiſh,</hi> and <hi>fowle</hi> are deſtroyed. For ſinnes he doth ſtretch out his hand vpon <hi>Iudah,</hi> and vpon all the inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15634:11"/>for ſinnes he doth <hi>worry</hi> the <hi>Sheepe,</hi> and <hi>ſmite</hi> the <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard.</hi> This is the firſt reaſon why <hi>Ioſias</hi> is ſmitten.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe of ſmiting <hi>Ioſias.</hi>
               </note>The ſecond reaſon that <hi>Ioſias</hi> was ſmitten, was, that <hi>hee might not ſee the miſery threatned to be brought vpon Iſraell;</hi> his <hi>eyes</hi> ſhould not ſee that <hi>euill.</hi> Euill muſt come but not in the dayes of <hi>Ioſias.</hi> The word of the Lord is good, (ſaith <hi>Hezekias</hi>) onely let peace be in my dayes. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> muſt be bond-ſlaues in the land of <hi>Egipt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſis.</note> but not till the <hi>Patriarkes</hi> ſleepe in peace. Tenne <hi>Tribes</hi> ſhall be diuided from the <hi>twelue,</hi> yet <hi>Salomons</hi> eyes ſhall firſt be ſhut. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed, but not till they who mourne in <hi>Zyon</hi> be marked.<note place="margin">Ezek. 9.4.</note> Al <hi>Italy</hi> grieuouſly troubled, but <hi>Ambroſe</hi> muſt firſt be at reſt. <hi>Africa</hi> ſhal be ſpoiled, but not till <hi>Auſtine</hi> deceaſe. <hi>Germany</hi> was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, but <hi>Luther</hi> firſt muſt peaceably &amp; honourably be buryed. <hi>England</hi> was perſecuted and fiered, but bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed King <hi>Edward</hi> muſt firſt be receiued into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome. God reſerueth his iuſt &amp; determinate plagues, and ſtayeth his Vyals till his appointed times. All the States of the World haue their <hi>Criticall</hi> dayes, and <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mactericall</hi> yeeres, beginnings, ſetled ſtations, declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and diſſolutions at Gods appointment.</p>
            <q>Certo veniunt ordine Parcae.<note place="margin">Seneca.</note>
            </q>
            <p>It was a ſpeech that commands <hi>admiration</hi> from vs, that God ſhould ſay to <hi>Lot,</hi> Get thee hence; I can doe nothing till thou art gone hence. Was the power of God limited by himſelfe? he did <hi>actiuely</hi> limit his power, it was not <hi>paſsiuely</hi> limitted by <hi>Lot; God</hi> did limit his wil;<note place="margin">Geneſis.</note> or rather, both were <hi>determinated,</hi> then <hi>limited</hi> or <hi>termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated.</hi> It exceedes our <hi>thoughts</hi> that he in ſo <hi>fauourable</hi> a Compaſſion will forbeare, for his loue to ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Seruant, the great wrath he hath laid vp in ſtore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15634:12"/>for a <hi>Nation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39 5. Gen. 30.27.</note> He doth not onely bleſſe <hi>Potiphar</hi> for <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and <hi>Laban</hi> for <hi>Iacob,</hi> but hold his hand, ſtay his Vials, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare his vengeance vpon <hi>Iſrael</hi> for <hi>Ioſias</hi> ſake; holy and reuerend be his name for euer.</p>
            <p>I haue <hi>numbred</hi> and <hi>weighed</hi> the words haſtily, and in the <hi>Scales</hi> of <hi>ſighes</hi> and <hi>ſorrow;</hi> let vs ſee what <hi>meaſure</hi> of them commeth to our <hi>ſhare.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> And firſt, was <hi>ſinne</hi> the cauſe of ſmiting the Shepheard? Indeede, <hi>Sinne</hi> is the ouerthrow of <hi>Iudgement,</hi> the <hi>ſtaine</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> the <hi>roote</hi> of all <hi>peruerſitie, infection</hi> of all <hi>actions</hi> &amp; <hi>affections:</hi> but is it ſo <hi>harmefull</hi> to vs, ſo <hi>hatefull</hi> to him, that is, the all-ſeeing, all-being, all-pure and ſacred <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> that not onely his owne Sonne, bleſſed for euer and euer, was ſmitten,<note place="margin">Eſay.</note> 
               <hi>propter ſcelus populi,</hi> as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh; but alſo thoſe excellent, and choiſe, and bleſſed Inſtruments of his glory, <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> are often-times taken away for the ſins of the people? Let vs all then looke into the <hi>Calender</hi> of theſe <hi>dayes,</hi> wee haue ſeene, and found, and felt their effects; and let vs <hi>obſerue</hi> whether the ſinnes of this Land, and eſpecially this <hi>Citie</hi> and <hi>Court,</hi> be not equall to any of any Land: ſee whether the <hi>ſins</hi> now be <hi>culpable,</hi> or <hi>damnable,</hi> winckt at onely by the <hi>eyes</hi> of men, or crying in the <hi>eares</hi> of Heauen. You ſhall finde them to be aſpiring, mounting, towring ſinnes: Sinnes of the higheſt eleuation; and thoſe <hi>ſins</hi> now <hi>committed,</hi> which in times paſt durſt not be <hi>named.</hi> Men like women, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men like Diuels, <hi>common;</hi> to ſalute and ſtab, kiſſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray, <hi>common;</hi> cheating, whoring, drinking, ſwearing as <hi>common</hi> as breathing.</p>
            <p>Neuer were ſuch <hi>varniſhes</hi> put vpon <hi>rotten cauſes,</hi> or <hi>Lawes</hi> made ſuch <hi>quirkes</hi> for mercenary wits; or <hi>goodnes</hi> ſo <hi>deformed, Iuſtice</hi> ſo <hi>guilty, Vertue</hi> ſo <hi>needy, Religion</hi> ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15634:12"/>
               <hi>ſcorned,</hi> or <hi>Whoredome</hi> ſo <hi>painted.</hi> In a word, to let paſſe the <hi>Couetouſneſſe</hi> of the rich, <hi>idleneſſe</hi> of the poore, <hi>want</hi> of age, <hi>wantonneſſe</hi> of youth, <hi>prophaneneſſe</hi> of all; I aske the honeſt <hi>Religious</hi> Soule that mourneth for the miſery of <hi>Zyon.</hi> Is it not ſtrange that after ſo long preaching of the Goſpel, there ſhould be ſuch an <hi>inundation</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> this generation of <hi>Vipers</hi> ſeeming to multiply in our time, as the <hi>Arrians</hi> did encreaſe in the time of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Fathers,</hi> who preached and wrote againſt them? <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiels</hi> Prophecie may ſeeme fulfilled, the Idol of indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is among vs; there be ſome <hi>Ancient Idolaters,</hi> ſome <hi>idolatrous</hi> women, ſome <hi>idolatrous Prieſts</hi> in our Land. Theſe be cauſes why our <hi>Ioſias</hi> was ſmitten: our ſinnes opened that <hi>Vena Baſilica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, would no other Sacrifice ſerue, but the death of <hi>Ioſias?</hi> No.<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.7.8</note> The former Prophet <hi>Zephany</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it plaine, in his 1. Chapter 7. and 8 verſes. <hi>The Lord hath prepared a</hi> Sacrifice, <hi>and in that day of the Lords</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice <hi>he will viſit the</hi> Princes, <hi>and the</hi> Kings <hi>Children.</hi> No other <hi>ſacrifice</hi> will ſerue but the branches of the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue</hi> tree, the bloſſomes of the <hi>Figge</hi> tree, the beautifull young <hi>Cedar,</hi> the glory of the <hi>Forreſt,</hi> the beauty of the <hi>Garland,</hi> the <hi>Coronet</hi> of <hi>ſucceſsion,</hi> the <hi>Patron</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> the <hi>ioy</hi> of the <hi>olde, hope</hi> of <hi>young, comfort</hi> of <hi>all.</hi> Nothing would ſerue but that precious <hi>Iewell,</hi> which Nature only ſhewed the world, and ſo put vp againe, that happy <hi>New Starre,</hi> new <hi>eye</hi> of Heauen, of whoſe ſtation and influence while we argued, it went out againe. Nothing muſt ſerue but <hi>Ioſias? Si ſic in viridi, quid fiet in arido?</hi> what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the <hi>negligent, ignorant, windy, emptie, ſhadowy</hi> Creatures, who liue to eate, and eate to play the Beaſts? He was taken from the euill to come vpon ſuch, to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15634:13"/>
               <hi>ioy</hi> he enioyes: Hee is gone to reſt with more tokens of Gods fauour then euer <hi>Ioſias</hi> had, his precious Soule is <hi>bathed</hi> in the <hi>precious bloud</hi> of his bleſſed Sauiour; <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> did <hi>here</hi> comfort him; <hi>Confidence</hi> did <hi>hence</hi> crowne him; annointed <hi>Cherub,</hi> bleſſed <hi>Angell,</hi> gracious <hi>Maſter,</hi> thou art now in <hi>glory,</hi> though wee poore <hi>ſcattered ſheepe</hi> haue loſt <hi>thee. Teares</hi> blind me, and <hi>ſighes</hi> chooke, and here I ceaſe; <hi>ſorrow</hi> doth ſilence me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Correct</hi> vs no more in thy <hi>fury</hi> O Lord, let not thine <hi>arrowes</hi> ſticke ſo faſt in vs, northy <hi>hand</hi> preſſe vs ſo down, leſt we be conſumed, and brought to nothing. <hi>Magnifie</hi> thy arme of <hi>Mercy,</hi> as thou haſt exalted thine arme of <hi>Iudgement:</hi> and let neuer the like loſſe come vpon vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>till thy Sonne our Sauiour come to vs againe.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <head>The ſecond Sermon.</head>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Matth. 26.31.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <q>The Sheepe of the flocke ſhall be ſcattered.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Elias</hi> was departing, the <hi>Whirlewinde</hi> mouing, the fiery <hi>Chariot</hi> mounting, and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> in his tranſmigration, <hi>ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inter viuos nec mortuos,</hi> (as <hi>Bias</hi> ſpake of <hi>Saylers</hi>) being not gone vp into the aire, as <hi>Moſes</hi> on the Mount, or rapt vp into the third heauens for a time, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but as <hi>Henoch</hi> before, ſo he <hi>vnder,</hi> the Law, caught vp into the heauens for euer.<note place="margin">2 King. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Elias</hi> with the ſame wordes that afterwards <hi>Ioaſh</hi> the King lamented <hi>Eliſha;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>O my father, my father, the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot of Iſraell, and the horſe-men thereof.</hi> A lamentation ſitting our loſſe, who haue loſt our <hi>Father,</hi> our <hi>Maiſter,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15634:13"/>the <hi>Cedar</hi> of Lebanon, and <hi>Chariot</hi> of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>In the 16. of <hi>Numbers,</hi> it was an heauy,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.49.</note> weighty iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that in ſo ſmall a time, ſo great a number as 14700 ſhould die; <hi>Moſes</hi> then cryeth out, as if with ſorrow ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his <hi>head,</hi> &amp; wringing his <hi>hands; There is wrath gone out from the Lord, the plague is begun.</hi> Wee will borrow the words of him, it is (miſerable men that we are) I ſay, it is our caſe; <hi>Wrath</hi> is gone from the <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>plague</hi> is begun. Now is a time of mourning, of cloathing our ſelues in <hi>ſacke cloth</hi> and <hi>aſhes;</hi> nay, in <hi>duſt</hi> and <hi>aſhes,</hi> and in the ſhadow of <hi>death,</hi> that as we ſpent our firſt dayes in ſinne, ſo wee may ſpend our laſt dayes in ſorrow. Is not wrath come from the Lord, when our <hi>Lilly</hi> of the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes is blaſted; our <hi>Roſe</hi> of the field is blemiſhed? I ſay not that our <hi>Oliue</hi> branch is cut off, but the <hi>Doue</hi> with the <hi>Oliue</hi> branch is fled from vs.</p>
            <p>We are the men whom <hi>Ieremy</hi> mentioneth in his <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations;</hi> we haue ſeene the affliction in the rod of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation; the breath of our <hi>noſthrils,</hi> the bleſſed of the Lord, is taken from vs; our <hi>daunce</hi> is turned into <hi>mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;</hi> and the <hi>crowne</hi> of our head is fallen:<note place="margin">Lam 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Woe vnto vs that euer we ſinned;</hi> our <hi>heart</hi> is heauy, and our <hi>eyes</hi> are dimme, becauſe this Mount of <hi>Zion</hi> ſhall be deſolate. My Text doth <hi>epitomize</hi> what euer my ſorrow can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince; <hi>The Shepherd is ſmitten, and the ſheepe of the flocke ſhall be ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue gathered ſo much <hi>dew</hi> of Meditation from the firſt part, as a day and night could yeeld my ſorrowfull head and heart to receiue: that was our <hi>Maiſters</hi> part; this next <hi>ours; The ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered.</hi> In ſpeaking whereof, as that wonder of miſery, the vnhappy Mother in the beſiege of Ieruſalem, hauing eaten one part of her
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15634:14"/>Childe, could not thinke of eating the other without vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable ſorrow; ſo aſſure your ſelues, my <hi>ſobs</hi> and <hi>throbs,</hi> and <hi>throwes</hi> will be many, before I am deliuered of this part, which will part vs all, the diſperſion of the Sheepe. <hi>I will ſmite the Shepherd, and the ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſheepe.</hi>] Silly, ſimple creatures, yet decent, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent creatures, quietly feeding in the Field, hearing the voyce of the <hi>Shepherd,</hi> yet fearing their rauenous Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, though they be together, though they haue both a ſhepherd and a fold; but when they ſhal <hi>[be ſcattered]</hi> their caſe is more miſerable, hauing no <hi>defence,</hi> no <hi>hope,</hi> no <hi>helpe,</hi> no <hi>ſafetie.</hi> Put both together, a <hi>ſhepheard,</hi> but he <hi>ſmitten; Sheepe,</hi> and they <hi>ſcattered,</hi> then you will ſay, this Text and our ſtate is the ſame that the <hi>Proclamation</hi> was in the Army after the death of the King of <hi>Iſrael; Get euery man to his Citie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 22.</note> 
               <hi>and euery man to his own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: for the ſhepherd is ſmitten, and the ſheepe ſhall be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</hi> The <hi>parts</hi> be already opened: In this <hi>remainder</hi> of the former worke, theſe two <hi>particulars</hi> fall in ſunder. Firſt, the <hi>denomination</hi> of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſeruants, <hi>ſheepe.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the <hi>diſperſion</hi> of theſe <hi>ſheepe:</hi> they ſhall be <hi>ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</hi> And firſt, for <hi>ſheepe,</hi> they be <hi>creatures,</hi> neither <hi>noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> nor <hi>fulſome.</hi> I will borrow but one authoritie for them, out of the <hi>liſt</hi> and <hi>limit</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>— Tonſa tacet,</l>
               <l>Carne iuuat, pelle, vellere, lacte, fimo,</l>
            </q>
            <p>In Sacrifices no creature ſo frequently offered; in the Sinne-<hi>offring,</hi> Peace-<hi>offring,</hi> Burnt-<hi>offring,</hi> Paſſe-<hi>ouer,</hi> Saboth <hi>offring,</hi> and eſpecially in the daily offring; euery day they offered a <hi>Lambe</hi> at morning,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num. 28.9.</hi> Lorinus in <hi>8</hi> Act. Apoſt.</note> and a <hi>Lambe</hi> at euening. <hi>Lorinus</hi> obſerueth it out of <hi>Chriſoſtome, Euthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15634:14"/>duſtine, Origen, Cyrill</hi> and others,<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>4.</hi> tract. in Ioan. Orig. hom. <hi>24.</hi> in Num. Chriſ. hom. <hi>37</hi> in Math.</note> 
               <hi>mact abant agnum iugis noſtri ſacrificij typum:</hi> And ſo not onely theſe, but <hi>Gaudentius, Paulinus,</hi> and <hi>Cyprian</hi> giue that common knowne reaſon, why a <hi>Lambe</hi> was ſo continually offered; namely, as a type of the offring of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who in 28. ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> is called the Lambe of God.</p>
            <p>For the name of Sheepe, <hi>Notatiſsima eſt dicendi forma,</hi> ſaith a Writer. In the 34. of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the Prophets are 13.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Buc.</hi> Ezek. 34.</note> times called <hi>ſhepherds,</hi> and the People 21. times alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>ſheepe:</hi> and in the laſt verſe the Lord expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe thus; <hi>Ye my ſheepe, ye the ſheepe of my paſture are men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 34.31</note> 
               <hi>and I am your God, ſaith the Lord God.</hi> The 23. <hi>Pſalme</hi> is plaine to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Lor. in Pſal.</note> a Pſalme truely called <hi>Dauidis Bucolicon;</hi> there you haue ſhepherd, ſheep, greene fields, ſtill waters, wayes, pathes, vallyes, ſhadowes, yea, the rod and ſhepheards crooke. The <hi>Lord</hi> is my ſhepheard,<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> hee ſhall reſt me in greene paſtures, he leadeth me by the ſtil waters, bringeth me into the pathes of righteouſnes, &amp;c. The Chalde <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> vnderſtands this Pſalme of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> deliuerance out of Egypt.<note place="margin">Cald. Par. Athanaſius.</note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> of their returne out of <hi>Babilon,</hi> here propheſied: ſome interpret this lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, reſting, guiding, feeding, to be the power of the <hi>Word,</hi> ſo <hi>Lyranus;</hi> ſome of the <hi>ſacraments,</hi> ſo S. <hi>Auſtine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyranus. Aug in Pſ. Athanaſ.</note> ſome of the <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> of Chriſt, ſo <hi>Nyſſenus: Athanaſius</hi> wiſheth <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> when he did enter into conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lords gracious direction, &amp; bountiful feeding, then thankefully to ſing this Pſalme. And Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> much grieued in his time,<note place="margin">Ambroſ lib. <hi>5</hi> de Sacra. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> that men not conſidering the bleſſing they receiued by being named the ſheepe of Gods flocke, did ſo often heare, and ſo little regard the bleſſing of this Pſalme. I leade you further then may ſeeme neceſſary in this Pſalme, but it is the ſweeteſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15634:15"/>and the apteſt proofe in Scripture for my purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eli. Scho. Nazian. in Orat. <hi>2.</hi> de Filio.</note>A <hi>Scholiaſt</hi> vpon <hi>Nazianzen</hi> expoundeth thoſe greene fields to be the Church, the graſſe the Word, the waters the Sacraments, the Paſtor <hi>God,</hi> the flocke the <hi>people,</hi> the rod and ſtaffe <hi>inſtruction</hi> and <hi>correction: deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> as hee concludeth, <hi>Deum eſſe Paſtorem, amiſſos reducentem, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractos obligantem, correptos corroborantem: God</hi> is that Shepherd, bringing backe the loſt, as <hi>Paul;</hi> ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the weake, as <hi>Peter;</hi> binding vp the broken in hart, as <hi>Matthew</hi> that followed him; <hi>Magdalen</hi> that annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him; the <hi>Theefe</hi> that confeſſed him. Gods ſheepe, ſometimes <hi>feeding,</hi> as in this <hi>Pſalme;</hi> ſometimes <hi>trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> as <hi>Iacobs flocke,</hi> ſometimes <hi>ſuffering,</hi> as our Sauiour foretold, as ſheepe <hi>appointed</hi> for the ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſheepe</hi> in my Text be the <hi>Diſciples; Matthew</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth ſo much;<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.32.</note> 
               <hi>Marke</hi> expreſſeth it; but S. <hi>Iohn</hi> more plainly thus, <hi>yee ſhall be ſcattered,</hi> the ſpeech being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> whom in that <hi>Goſpell</hi> he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his ſheepe, his <hi>flocke,</hi> his fold: yet it is but <hi>puſillus grex,</hi> a little little flocke; little indeed, becauſe ſo few, the number but twelue, as of <hi>Patriarkes</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> as of the twelue Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> twelue fountaines of <hi>Elim;</hi> twelue foundations of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> twelue ſignes of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> They be <hi>Pauci, pauperes, puſilli,</hi> Poore ſheep, poore ſilly ſoules, to be ſent our among thoſe <hi>rauenous blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeking blood-ſucking</hi> Wolues.</p>
            <p>It was the <hi>laſt Sermon</hi> that euer Chriſt preached on earth to his <hi>Diſciples;</hi> it was as his farewell, the <hi>night</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſuffred: the laſt glimpſe of a <hi>Candle</hi> is often moſt bright; the laſt glance and luſtre of the Sunne ſomtimes moſt cleere. They ſhould now haue expected ſome ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full newes; all their life before was ſorrowfull, now they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15634:15"/>might looke for ſome <hi>Legacie,</hi> that Chriſt would haue bleſſed them, as old <hi>Iacob</hi> did. But our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> who had formerly told them there was no comfort for them in the world, becauſe they were not of the world; that they were but as ſheepe among Wolues, giueth them no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther title in his laſt <hi>Legacie</hi> but <hi>ſheepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> Whence this obſeruation ariſeth, <hi>that the ſeruants of Chriſt ought to be cleane, quiet, ſimple, and peaceable in the world;</hi> for <hi>they are but ſheepe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen.</note> In ſheepe ſaith <hi>Origen</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed <hi>Cogitationum munditia;</hi> cleane, honeſt, ſanctified cogitations ought to be in Chriſts ſeruants. In ſheepe, ſaith <hi>Gregory,</hi> is obſerued <hi>Actionum innocentia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg.</note> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, religious, innocentactions ought to proceede from Chriſts ſheepe. I could multiply and increaſe fathers &amp; ſonnes for the manifeſtation of this point, but this onely reaſon ſhall ſerue, Chriſt himſelfe was ſuch a ſheepe, and therefore ſuch ought we to be. He was not <hi>ouis,</hi> but <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ouis,</hi> for he was <hi>agnus Dei,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lorinus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lor. in Act. Ap.</note> And ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wondereth hereat, <hi>Hoc mirum eſt, Chriſtum et agnum eſſe, et ouem eſſe, et paſtorem eſſe.</hi> Chriſt indeede was ſo, and neuer any other ſo. Which is eaſily made plaine; for though wee ſhould not ſpeake without <hi>admiration,</hi> nor thinke without <hi>adoration</hi> of all the myſteries of our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption:</hi> yet in the <hi>deepe</hi> well of this myſterie, euen hee that hath nothing to <hi>draw,</hi> may vnderſtand it. As in the Kingly, Prieſtly, Propheticall offices of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hee did communicate two of thoſe offices to <hi>ſome,</hi> but neuer all the three to any. <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Prieſt</hi> not a <hi>Prophet: Moyſes</hi> was a <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> as the Pſalme ſpeaketh, <hi>Moyſes</hi> among his <hi>Prieſts,</hi> but was not a <hi>King: Dauid</hi> was a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> but not a <hi>Prieſt.</hi> So the ſame <hi>Dauid</hi> was a <hi>ſhepheard,</hi> Pſal. 78.72. and a <hi>ſheep,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.72</note> Pſal.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15634:16"/>119.176. but he was neuer called a <hi>Lambe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.176.</note> this name was neuer giuen to any but to our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> vntill the day of his <hi>Aſcention,</hi> when he commanded <hi>Peter</hi> to feed his Lambes: and yet not they neither were called lambes in the ſame ſenſe and meaning that our Sauiour was.</p>
            <p>It is obſerued,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.</note> in the Emblematicall bleſſings, that <hi>Iacob</hi> left his children, <hi>Iudah</hi> as a Lyon, <hi>Dan</hi> as a Serpent, <hi>Iſſachar</hi> an Aſſe, <hi>Nepthali</hi> a Hinde, &amp;c. hee giueth none the motto <hi>tanquam ouis,</hi> none of them is called a <hi>ſheep,</hi> or a <hi>lambe,</hi> and yet out of <hi>Iuda,</hi> whoſe <hi>Embleme</hi> was the <hi>Lyon,</hi> Chriſt came, who was both the <hi>Lyon</hi> &amp; the <hi>Lambe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sauiour in the two <hi>Sacraments</hi> of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords ſupper,</hi> among other miracles, wrought theſe two: he bleſſed the <hi>fowles</hi> of heauen in <hi>Baptiſme</hi> by the <hi>Doue</hi> that deſcended on him: hee bleſſed the <hi>beasts</hi> of the <hi>field</hi> in the <hi>Paſchall lambe,</hi> at the <hi>laſt ſupper</hi> eaten by him. But the <hi>vnſpeakable bleſſing</hi> whereby he hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not onely his <hi>Diſciples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſoſt.</note> and their <hi>ſucceſſors,</hi> but all his ſeruants, is this, that they are his flocke, his fowle, his lambes, and his ſheepe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> Is it ſo then? be the <hi>ſeruants</hi> of Chriſt his ſheepe? Firſt then, how ought they to liue, an honeſt, ſimple, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent life in theſe <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>worſt,</hi> and <hi>abominable</hi> dayes? Chriſt was the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and <hi>he hath left vs an example to follow his ſteps,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.</note> as S. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth: but alas how farre are we from his <hi>example,</hi> from his <hi>ſteps? Paſsibus aequis</hi> none can follow him I confeſſe, were all the <hi>righteous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> of the Patriarkes, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs and Saints put together in one man, yet it were impoſſible to follow him with <hi>equal paces.</hi> I will not preſcribe his <hi>miſery,</hi> his <hi>pouerty</hi> to you; I know you will not follow it; you eſteeme it a <hi>heauy yoke,</hi> his <hi>miſery,</hi> his <hi>pouerty,</hi> was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15634:16"/>vnſupportable; he was <hi>Lord</hi> of all things, yet inioyed <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> he had not a <hi>houſe</hi> to be borne in, he borrowed a <hi>ſtable;</hi> not a <hi>bed</hi> to be laid in, he borrowed a <hi>cratch;</hi> not a <hi>veſſell</hi> to drinke in, he borrowed a <hi>pitcher;</hi> not a <hi>roome</hi> to eate his <hi>paſſeouer</hi> in, he borrowed a <hi>parlour;</hi> not a <hi>graue</hi> to be layd in, he borrowed a <hi>ſepulcher.</hi> Of theſe things you will aske me, as the Poet, <hi>quis legit,</hi> who can read theſe things? or rather as <hi>Eſay, quis credit,</hi> in ſpeaking of theſe who will beleeue our report? I doe not forbeare to preſſe the imitation of this: I preſcribe his <hi>chaſtitie;</hi> he was the Virgin-Son of the Virgin-Mother,<note place="margin">Aug. de Temp.</note> imitate this. <hi>Cum Virginis filio non erit tua luxuria:</hi> Chaſtity becomes his ſheepe. I preſcribed his charitie; hee healed <hi>Malchus</hi> eare, though he drew vpon him; he ſaluted <hi>Iudas</hi> by the name of friend when he betrayed him; he prayed for his enemies when they crucified him. <hi>Cum charitatis authore non erit malitia tua:</hi> Charity becomes his ſheepe. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his meekeneſſe and <hi>humility;</hi> all the practiſe of his life was <hi>humility,</hi> and his leſſon was <hi>humility;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Temp.</note> 
               <hi>Learne of me to be humble and meeke. Cum humilitatis doctore non erit ſuperbia tua;</hi> Humilitie becomes his ſheepe.</p>
            <p>It was not long before <hi>Chriſts death,</hi> that the <hi>Diſciples</hi> did propoſe a ſtrange queſtion among themſelues, <hi>ſtriuing for prioritie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marke 9.</note> they diſputed who ſhould be the <hi>greateſt</hi> among them. A <hi>wonder,</hi> that two ſuch <hi>ambitious twinnes</hi> ſhould be among the <hi>Diſciples:</hi> I pray God there neuer hath beene any ſuch queſtion of <hi>contention</hi> and <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> among any of you. Sure I am, we were all <hi>growne proud,</hi> and placed our <hi>ſtrength</hi> in the <hi>arme</hi> of <hi>fleſh,</hi> and that for this and other ſinnes, the Lord hath taken our <hi>ſweete</hi> and bleſſed <hi>Maſter</hi> from vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, are ye ſheep of one flocke? O then be of one
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15634:17"/>minde, in vnity, amitie, vnanimitie: the places are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, where Chriſt his ſeruants are called members of one <hi>bodie, ſheepe</hi> of one <hi>fold, branches</hi> of one <hi>Vine:</hi> how is it then that <hi>Caine</hi> will ſeeke to kill <hi>Abell,</hi> or <hi>Iſmaell</hi> to ieſt at <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Epheſ. 2 Epheſ. Iohn.</note> or <hi>Eſau</hi> to hate <hi>Iacob,</hi> or <hi>Ioab</hi> to ſtab <hi>Amaga? Children, Brethren, dearely beloued,</hi> be the phraſes of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> to thoſe that are Chriſts ſeruants.</p>
            <p>It is well worth the obſeruation, that one noteth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Church Lyturgie, in euery article of deuotion, that we come to performe in the Church, the ſalutation ſtill is, <hi>Dearely beloued:</hi> a phraſe vſed in the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Communion, the adminiſtration of Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, the ſolemnizing of Marriage, at the buriall of the Dead, at the generall Commination: How ſhall your conſcience beare you witneſſe that the Church ſpeaketh to you, as <hi>Dearely beloued,</hi> if there be an enuious, malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſcandalous, ſlaunderous, pining, repining, vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſpirit amongſt you? Remember, <hi>branches</hi> muſt <hi>grow</hi> together, members <hi>agree</hi> together, ſheep <hi>feede</hi> together.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, is it ſo, that ye be <hi>Chriſts ſheepe?</hi> then heare Chriſts <hi>voyce:</hi> it is one of the true notes of <hi>Chriſts true ſheepe, Audiunt vocem meam,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt: Audiunt &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem mea: Audiunt,</hi> that is, a neceſſitie of hearing.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14. Matth. Pſalm. 119.</note> 
               <hi>Faith</hi> commeth by hearing, <hi>knowledge</hi> commeth by hearing, <hi>comfort</hi> commeth by hearing: They that ſtop their eares, and wil not heare, are not Chriſts ſheepe. Though thou be <hi>lame</hi> as <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> or <hi>blinde</hi> for a time as <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>dumbe</hi> as <hi>Zachary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 9.25</note> yet thou mayſt be in Chriſts fould: but if the <hi>deafe diuell</hi> haue poſſeſſed thee, if thou ſtop thy eares, thou art none of his flocke.</p>
            <p>What <hi>ioy</hi> had <hi>Dauid</hi> in hearing but of going to Church?<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> 
               <hi>It did me good,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>when I heard them ſay we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15634:17"/>will goe to Ieruſalem. Audiunt vocem ſuam,</hi> not onely they muſt heare, but heare his <hi>voyce:</hi> therefore our Sauiour gaue a double caueat, <hi>quid, &amp; quomodo:</hi> In <hi>Marke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 4.24. Luke 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed what ye heare,</hi> there is <hi>quid:</hi> in <hi>Luke, Take heed how ye heare, quomodo.</hi> If euer it were a time to ſet a watch at thoſe open ports of our eares, theſe be the dayes; wherein ſome like the ſouldiours of <hi>Gaſtro,</hi> are armed with the aduerſaries arguments, as they were with the enemies armour. Some coyning <hi>inuentions,</hi> of which ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> I haue hared <hi>inuentions;</hi> others with <hi>traditions,</hi> of which Chriſt forewarneth; others with <hi>infallible notes</hi> of <hi>ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of Scripture; <hi>which notes,</hi> howſoeuer they ſeeme to haue warrant out of <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vine. Lirin.</note> yet of the three, he acknowledgeth that <hi>Heretikes</hi> haue claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two of them, the <hi>Arrians</hi> vniuerſalitie, and the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> antiquitie; and <hi>denies</hi> not <hi>but that the third</hi> may be challenged by <hi>inueterate hereſies</hi> alſo: and I ad further, that the <hi>Diuels</hi> may pleade for it Conſent, and not He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes onely; for <hi>Sathan</hi> is not diuided againſt <hi>Sathan:</hi> wherefore let not any <hi>voyce</hi> be here to be <hi>beleeued;</hi> but that one voyce, <hi>vnam regulam,</hi> Scripture, as worthily <hi>Vincentius</hi> in his 41 Chapter doth plainly deliuer.<note place="margin">Vine. Lirin.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, be ye all Chriſts <hi>ſeruants,</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſheepe,</hi> by <hi>honest</hi> liuing, <hi>heartie</hi> louing, and <hi>diligent</hi> hearing. So much of the firſt part.</p>
            <p>
               <label>The ſecond part.</label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme.</note>
               <hi>[The ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered.] Diſsipentur inimici,</hi> let his enemes be ſcattered: <hi>Quid meruere oues,</hi> what haue his poore ſheep <hi>deſerued? Miſery</hi> enough to be ſuch <hi>help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe creatures</hi> as ſheepe; but ſcattered,<note place="margin">Lorinus.</note> 
               <hi>diſperdere</hi> is <hi>bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdere,</hi> this is a greater wane of <hi>miſery;</hi> poore diſciples, now they might ſit <hi>ſobbing</hi> day and night, <hi>breaking</hi> their <hi>breaſts</hi> with <hi>beating, wearing</hi> their <hi>hands</hi> with <hi>wringing,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:15634:18"/>their <hi>hearts</hi> aking with <hi>ſighes,</hi> and their <hi>eyes</hi> ſtreaming with ſorrowes; bruiſed <hi>reeds</hi> the ſtaffe of their <hi>comfort,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them; the <hi>Children</hi> of the Bride <hi>chamber,</hi> mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for the abſence of the <hi>Bridegroome; Lambes</hi> ſent out into the vaſt world among <hi>Wolues;</hi> poore ſoules, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, diſcomforted creatures, hearing their <hi>woe,</hi> feeling their <hi>want;</hi> ſolitary are they now to be left, that had beene <hi>his dayly waiters,</hi> that had been the witneſſes of his <hi>miracles: Looke</hi> vpon the <hi>Mother,</hi> the neere <hi>kinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman</hi> of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> leading her two ſons to be <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred</hi> to our <hi>Sauiour</hi> his ſeruice; did they thinke of this <hi>ſcattering? Looke</hi> vpon his Diſciples <hi>diſputing</hi> for <hi>prioritie</hi> who ſhould be <hi>greater;</hi> did they thinke of this ſcattering? <hi>Looke</hi> vpon thoſe two Diſciples in <hi>Luke,</hi> trauelling to <hi>Emaus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 24.13</note> how were they deiected, when they remembred this ſcattering? they truſted it had beene He that ſhould haue deliuered <hi>Iſrael.</hi> All the life of his <hi>Diſciples</hi> was a ſcattering, iourneying, troubleſome life: they were ſtil in <hi>progreſſe;</hi> our <hi>Sauiour had no ſtanding houſe,</hi> but <hi>heauen.</hi> He promiſed them in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Quando ſedebit filius hominis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>vos ſedebitis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> But when did he ſit, ſaith <hi>Bernard?</hi> He had no eaſe, no place to reſt on. Theſe his ſorrowfull, and as it were forlorne followers, had heard <hi>Chriſt</hi> oft, that he was the light of the <hi>world,</hi> and the bread of <hi>life,</hi> that he had <hi>ouercome the world,</hi> yet ſhall they beſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: It had beene enough to haue cauſed their hope to <hi>vaniſh</hi> like <hi>ſmoake,</hi> and their <hi>Faith</hi> to wither like <hi>graſſe,</hi> &amp; death to ſting them to the <hi>death,</hi> Hell to <hi>triumph</hi> ouer them: but they were <hi>ſheepe,</hi> therefore <hi>ſilent,</hi> they expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late not, but obediently and patiently heare their inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miſerie; <hi>The ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>
               </label> The obſeruation collected from the world; <hi>ſcattered,</hi> is,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15634:18"/>that <hi>the ſeruants of Christ must be content to be ſeuered from their fellowes, and friends, and comforts whatſoeuer.</hi> One muſt be like a <hi>Pellican</hi> in the wilderneſſe, another like a <hi>Storcke</hi> in the deſart, ſome like the <hi>Turtle</hi> on the houſe-top, others like <hi>Doues</hi> in the holes of the rockes, they cannot be together, but like grapes after a vintage, here one, there one. The indorſement of <hi>God</hi> to his Saints, is like that of S. <hi>Peter</hi> to the Iewes,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>To the ſtrangers diſperſed.</hi> Theſe <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were diſperſed, and tranſlated into diuers countries, <hi>Peter</hi> into <hi>Antioch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb.</note> 
               <hi>Iames</hi> to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Iohn</hi> into <hi>Aſia, Andrew</hi> into <hi>Scithia, Philip</hi> into <hi>Gallia, Bartholomew</hi> into <hi>Armenia, Mathew</hi> into <hi>Ethiopia, Thomas</hi> into <hi>India, Iude</hi> into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and <hi>Simon Zelotes</hi> into <hi>Meſopotamia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was a diſperſion, and diſſolution, more horrid then this; for in this there was a <hi>bleſsing;</hi> but the <hi>ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> (I meane) was of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> was a full meaſure of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, that when the <hi>Iewes</hi> had bin aſſailed oft, as may be found ſixe times in the old <hi>Teſtament,</hi> at the length their vtter deſtruction, their finall <hi>downefall</hi> and funerall came vpon them; the <hi>deſolation</hi> of their country, <hi>detestation</hi> of their <hi>Nation,</hi> abhorring of their <hi>Names,</hi> the ſcattering, fettering, conſuming of their Citie, Temple, peace, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, and of all bleſſings, ſodainly ouer-tooke them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Prophecy of them was fulfilled, <hi>Behold, your houſe ſhall be deſolate vnto you:</hi> for neyther the <hi>aged</hi> for their <hi>gray-haires</hi> found <hi>reuerence,</hi> nor the <hi>ſuckling reliefe</hi> for his <hi>infant</hi> innocentage, nor <hi>Matrone,</hi> nor <hi>Prieſt</hi> nor <hi>Virgin,</hi> nor <hi>Senatour,</hi> for <hi>Modeſtie</hi> or <hi>order,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudolph.</note> found any <hi>pitie.</hi> But this is no ſuch ſcattering.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>diſperſio tegumenti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> and <hi>diſperſio Tritici</hi> the <hi>winde</hi> ſcattereth the <hi>chaffe,</hi> the <hi>Husbandman</hi> ſcattereth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15634:19"/>the <hi>Wheate;</hi> the <hi>Wicked</hi> are the <hi>chaffe,</hi> as in the Pſalmes &amp;. Prophets frequently;<note place="margin">Oſca. Ier. Ezek.</note> the <hi>Godly</hi> are the <hi>Wheate,</hi> ſowen, reaped, threſhed, ground to powder; yet howſoeuer ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, Gods promiſe was ſtill, <hi>Capillum de capite iuſti non periturum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> nay, more, <hi>Quodcunque faciet, proſpere faciet:</hi> he not onely careth for the <hi>bones,</hi> that the <hi>bones which he hath broken may reioyce;</hi> but the ſhadow of <hi>Peter</hi> ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the <hi>ſicke;</hi> the <hi>handkercher</hi> of <hi>Paul</hi> deliuer the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed; the <hi>Cloake</hi> of <hi>Elias</hi> diuide the <hi>Waters;</hi> and the <hi>Bones</hi> of <hi>Elizeus</hi> reuiue the <hi>dead:</hi> and as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake by his <hi>experience:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor.</note> As vnknowne yet knowne; as dying, yet behold we liue; as <hi>chaſtened,</hi> yet behold not killed; as <hi>ſorrowing,</hi> and yet <hi>reioycing;</hi> as <hi>poore,</hi> and yet making many <hi>rich;</hi> as hauing nothing, and yet <hi>enioying</hi> al things: in a word, as <hi>ſcattered,</hi> yet comforted.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>name</hi> that euer was giuen, the name <hi>Adam,</hi> was a name of <hi>ſcattering:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Ioan.</note> it contaynes, ſaith <hi>Auſtine,</hi> in foure <hi>Letters,</hi> the foure <hi>Parts</hi> of the World, Eaſt, Weſt, North, South; yet the Lord promiſeth to gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſcattered flocke of Iſrael, from the Eaſt, Weſt, North, and South.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> I haue ended my <hi>weake</hi> &amp; weather-beaten Mediatations vpon this Text. <hi>Application</hi> muſt begin where <hi>Meditation</hi> ends When our <hi>Sauiour</hi> entered into the <hi>Synagogue</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Saboth</hi> day,<note place="margin">Luke 4.18.</note> hee opened the Booke vpon thoſe wordes of <hi>Eſay, The ſpirit of the Lord is vpon mee, he hath ſent me, that I ſhould heale the broken hearted, &amp;c.</hi> And he ſhut the Booke, and ſaid, this day is this <hi>Scripture</hi> fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in your eares: <hi>Beloued,</hi> if euer <hi>Scripture</hi> were fulfilled in your eares; if euer <hi>Scripture</hi> made your hearts to ake, and your eares to tingle, this is the <hi>day,</hi> this the <hi>Text:</hi> if euer any <hi>Scripture</hi> did take downe the <hi>creſt</hi> of <hi>Pride,</hi> and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15634:19"/>abate the <hi>edge</hi> of <hi>Reuenge,</hi> to moue you <hi>throughly</hi> to leaue and loath the <hi>World,</hi> this is it: <hi>I will ſmite the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, and the ſheepe ſhall be ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, why is there not a generall thaw through-out all <hi>mankinde?</hi> why in this <hi>debaſhed Ayre doe not all thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Time</hi> lookes vpon vs with <hi>watry</hi> eyes, <hi>diſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueld</hi> lockes, and <hi>heauie</hi> diſmall lookes; now that the Sunne is gone out of our Firnament, the <hi>ioy,</hi> the <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is departed?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
               </label> Honourable, Worſhipfull, worthy <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the greatneſſe of your <hi>Offices,</hi> or in the neereneſſe of your <hi>attendance,</hi> liued vnder the <hi>Branches</hi> of our <hi>Princely Cedar:</hi> to <hi>you this</hi> is a <hi>diſsolution,</hi> not a <hi>diſperſion; diſperdere</hi> is not <hi>perdere</hi> with you, <hi>you</hi> onely returne to your owne <hi>Families</hi> to drinke of your owne <hi>Vines;</hi> and to eate vnder your owne <hi>fig-trees;</hi> yet remember hereafter, as the wiſe <hi>Egyptians</hi> did beſtow more on their <hi>Tombes</hi> then <hi>Houſes,</hi> ſo hereafter diſpoſe of more time for conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of <hi>death,</hi> then of prouiſion for the things of this <hi>life:</hi> Let <hi>mortalitie</hi> be your <hi>meditation,</hi> you are but <hi>earth;</hi> your <hi>beſt</hi> cloaths, <hi>earth,</hi> wormes made them; your <hi>beſt fed</hi> bodies, <hi>earth,</hi> wormes muſt eate them. You may ſay, <hi>Vidimus ſtellam,</hi> we haue ſeene his Starre, and <hi>vidimus gloriam,</hi> we haue ſeene his glory; you ſaw it <hi>riſing</hi> and <hi>ſetting,</hi> you will now beleeue, that that GOD who hath called Princes <hi>Gods;</hi> he, <hi>qui homines coeleſtibus aequat,</hi> hath made Princes but <hi>men; quia ſceptra ligonibus aequat.</hi> You haue ſerued (and therein your poſteritie may reioyce) the moſt <hi>religious, gracious, holy, chaste; vertuous, valerous Prince</hi> of his growth, that euer the Chriſtian world enioyed, yet you ſee HEE is departed: ſeaſon therefore this lumpe of luggage, all worldly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15634:20"/>thoughts with the remembrance of death. Embrace all holy acts of <hi>religion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 37.</note> keepe <hi>innocencie,</hi> and doe that which is <hi>iuſt,</hi> and ſeeke <hi>peace, for this ſhall bring a man ioy at the laſt.</hi> You are all of you I hope, to ſerue another <hi>Prince,</hi> I doubt not you are in <hi>Check-roll</hi> already; miſtake me not, I meane no other <hi>Prince</hi> then the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> ſpoke of in <hi>Eſay;</hi> I meane no other <hi>Roll,</hi> but his booke of <hi>life: Reioyce in this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa 9 6.</note> 
               <hi>that your names be written in the booke of life;</hi> that ſeruice is <hi>heritage:</hi> inſtead of your white ſtaues, you ſhall haue <hi>Palmes</hi> in your hands, and your enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment will be, <hi>Good ſeruants and faithfull, you haue beene faithfull in a little, I will make you rulers ouer much, enter into your Maſters ioy.</hi> This <hi>ioy</hi> the Lord in mercy, in his due time, graunt vnto you.</p>
            <p>You of the <hi>middle ſort,</hi> whoſe <hi>wound</hi> is not <hi>mortall,</hi> and yet are <hi>ready</hi> to <hi>ſinke</hi> vnder the <hi>burthen</hi> of this <hi>ſorrow,</hi> as hauing <hi>loſt</hi> the moſt incomparable <hi>Prince,</hi> that euer the <hi>World</hi> had: you that ſetled your <hi>thoughts,</hi> and hoping to haue ſeene him the <hi>Head ouer many Nations,</hi> haue ſaid to your <hi>ſoules,</hi> vnder the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of his <hi>wings</hi> we ſhall be <hi>ſafe; here</hi> wil we dwell for euer. Let your <hi>dare</hi>-bought <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> teach you the leſſon that <hi>Dauid,</hi> a great <hi>Prince,</hi> gaue to his People;<note place="margin">Pſal. 146.</note> 
               <hi>Truſt not in Princes,</hi> for they be <hi>ſons of men,</hi> there is no <hi>health</hi> in them, their <hi>breath</hi> departeth, and euery one of them <hi>returneth</hi> to his earth.<note place="margin">Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Si dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſit aliquid mirabil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ſaith a Father, If a man may ſpeake any thing worthy of the greateſt <hi>admiration,</hi> it is this, <hi>Truſt not in Princes,</hi> they themſelues are not in <hi>ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> their <hi>ſublimitie</hi> is but <hi>ſublunary;</hi> they are within the <hi>verge;</hi> the Earth hath prouided an <hi>Auello</hi> for euery of them to be laid in: yeeld <hi>them faithfulnes</hi> and <hi>obedience,</hi> but ſettle not in <hi>them</hi> your <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>confidence.</hi> Yeelde
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15634:20"/>them <hi>duty, tribute,</hi> yea, your <hi>goods</hi> and <hi>liues,</hi> but withall remember,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 146.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that puts his truſt in the Lord, and hath the God of</hi> lacob <hi>for his refuge:</hi> liue <hi>honeſt, holy, religious liues,</hi> but a while; the end is at hand, we ſhal <hi>all</hi> meete in <hi>aequalitie</hi> with our bleſſed <hi>Maiſter</hi> in <hi>glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You <hi>poore ſoules,</hi> the poore ſilly <hi>ſheepe</hi> of his <hi>flocke,</hi> who was wont to giue you <hi>meate</hi> in due ſeaſon; you that like thoſe in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> doe <hi>ariſe, and cry in the night,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lament. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and in the beginning of the watch poure out your harts like water, &amp; lift your eyes to heauen, for your ſelues, your wiues, and children:</hi> Take the counſell of <hi>Dauid; Truſt in the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> 
               <hi>and being good, commit thy waies vnto the Lord; waite pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently vpon the Lord, hope in him, and he ſhall bring it to paſſe: Truſt in the Lord, and verily thou ſhalt be fed.</hi> Heare <hi>Dauids</hi> example, <hi>I haue been young</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but now am old, yet I neuer ſaw the righteous forſaken, nor their ſeede begging their bread. Honeſty</hi> is the beſt <hi>patrimonie,</hi> leaue but a good report of an honeſt life behinde you, and your Children then haue ſufficient Legacies.</p>
            <p>All of you, <hi>beloued,</hi> that are in this valley of <hi>teares</hi> to heare mee this day, repent you of your former liues, turne from the wickedneſſe of your <hi>wayes,</hi> or elſe yee may feare a more fearefull ſcattering.</p>
            <p>The <hi>outrage</hi> of <hi>apparell, ſurquedry</hi> in <hi>meate, choiſe</hi> of new <hi>oathes,</hi> new <hi>exchange</hi> of <hi>ſins,</hi> &amp; the <hi>ſluce</hi> of <hi>vengeance</hi> that <hi>hell</hi> hath opened,<note place="margin">Since the yee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> haue brought many fearefull <hi>ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terings</hi> among vs within theſe few yeeres: the death of nine <hi>Counſellers</hi> of State, ſixteene <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the Church, fifteene <hi>Iudges</hi> of the Law, &amp; in one yeere, in this one <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> thirty ſeauen thouſand three hundred &amp; two, ſtroken with the <hi>Plague</hi> of Peſtilence,<note place="margin">Lady <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Lady <hi>Sop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia.</hi>
               </note> and which is more then al this, <hi>three of his Maieſties Children,</hi> the hope &amp; ioy to all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15634:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>true hearted Subiects,<note place="margin">Prince Henry, who dyed in the nineteenth yeere of his his age, the 6. of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember,</hi> 1612 and was hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> the 7. day of <hi>December</hi> following.</note> is taken away from among vs: &amp; which equals all other <hi>loſſes, Iſaac</hi> is <hi>offered, Ichabod,</hi> our glory, is <hi>departed, Prince Henry</hi> is <hi>deceaſed, whom</hi> if euer any of vs in his moſt <hi>obſeruant repoſed thoughts</hi> ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, let his right <hi>hand</hi> rot, and forget her cunning, and the harpe of his <hi>Tongue</hi> hang vp for euer in the roofe of his <hi>mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O God,</hi> how haſt thou plagued vs, as<note n="*" place="margin">Lament 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremy</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned euen in the <hi>ſolempne day?</hi> In that <hi>Moneth</hi> thou once gaueſt vs <hi>Queene Elizaheth,</hi> to take away Prince <hi>Henry?</hi> In that <hi>Moneth</hi> thou gaueſt vs Noble Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> the ſucceeding <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> in that <hi>Moneth</hi> to take away his bleſſed <hi>Brother?</hi> In the <hi>Moneth</hi> thou didſt preſerue vs from that furious ſulphureous <hi>plot</hi> of our enemies, in the ſame <hi>Moneth</hi> are wee, to our great <hi>ſorrowes,</hi> inſulted on by our <hi>Enemies?</hi> Hadſt thou not left vs a <hi>remnant,</hi> we had ben like to <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorh. Wherefore good Lord looke downe from Heauen, behold and viſit vs, looke vpon that Vine thy right hand hath planted; bleſſe the roote and branches of the Royall remnant: let the light of thy Countenance ſhine euer in the Sunne, and Moone and Stars of this Firmament; let neuer be wanting one of this race to ſit vpon the Brittiſh Throne, till the Sunne hath runne his laſt race, and the world hath finiſhed his last courſe. Say thou</hi> Amen, <hi>thou faithfull witneſſe of Heauen, to the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of vs poore, wretched, afflicted, miſerable ſoules: Say</hi> Amen <hi>thou Truth, and witneſſe of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to our Petitions that come not out of fained lips; and let Heauen and Earth ſeale it, and ſay,</hi> Amen, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:21"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15634:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
